JD PIRTLE | CURRICULUM VITAE

1523 N. Cleveland Ave. #4S Chicago, IL 60610 t| 312-508-0561 e| jdpirtle@gmail.com w| jdpirtle.com

PROFILE

Artist and researcher highly skilled in the design and creation of algorithmic, interactive applications and artworks. Passionate investigator and user of emerging technologies. Researcher in a world-renowned advanced visualization laboratory. Extremely comfortable in the command line.

EDUCATION

MFA | New Media Arts/Electronic Visualization, 2009-2011

University of Illinois at Chicago | adweb.aa.uic.edu

Master of Fine Arts in Electronic Visualization and New Media. Areas of concentration included stereoscopic animation for virtual reality environments, physical computing, algorithmic audio composition, rapid prototyping (CNC, 3D printing, laser cutting/etching), computer vision and generative fine art. Studied with Daniel Sauter, Sabrina Raaf and Drew Browning.

BFA | Digital Art and Experimental Media with Departmental Honors, 2005-2008

Center for Digital Arts and Experimental Media (DXARTS), University of Washington | dxarts.washington.edu Five-year Bachelor of Fine Arts in Digital Art and Experimental Media with honors. First ever recipient of an honor's undergraduate degree from this department. Areas of concentration included stereoscopic animation and cinema, digital signal processing, algorithmic audio composition, physical computing and generative art. Studied with Shawn Brixey, Richard Karpin, Juan Pampin, Josh Parmenter and Stephanie Andrews.

RESEARCH AND PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Artist and Researcher | Electronic Visualization Laboratory, 2011-Present

University of Illinois at Chicago | evl.uic.edu

Role: Artist and Researcher in advanced visualization and multichannel audio in an interdisciplinary laboratory that unites computer science, art, electrical engineering, biology, and communications

- Collaborating on design, implementation and construction of CAVE2 Virtual Reality Environment, a 72-display immersive virtual reality environment.
- Design and implementation of 22-channel audio system (20.2)
- Authored software for creating 22-channel multichannel audio
- · Development of interactive multitouch applications on large scale, high-resolution display walls

Research Assistant | Electronic Visualization Laboratory, 2010-2011

University of Illinois at Chicago

Role: Graduate research assistant

- · Collaborated on interactive multitouch applications on large scale, high-resolution display walls
- · Designed and implemented multichannel audio systems and software
- Designed and developed websites and databases

Teaching Assistant | Advanced Electronic Visualization and Critique, 2010

Graduate Seminar, University of Illinois at Chicago

Role: Teaching assistant for graduate level course that culminated in solo exhibitions on the The Jackman Goldwasser Catwalk Gallery at the Hyde Park Arts Center

- Assisted graduate students in the creation of large, interactive artworks designed for a 70 foot projected façade
- Configured software for controlling the cluster of computers driving the projected façade

IT/Creative Technologist | Teams Design Chicago, 2009-2010

Chicago, IL | teamsdesign.com/usa/

Role: IT and creative technologist in large industrial design firm

- Provided creative technical support to designers working with Rhino and Solidworks
- Designed and implemented interactive applications, including a large multitouch conference room wall
- System administrator of network and storage servers

Visiting Artist and Instructor | DXARTS, 2009

Center for Digital Arts and Experimental Media (DXARTS), University of Washington | dxarts.washington.edu Role: Instructor of record of 3 Space: Special Topics in 3D Computer Arts

• Taught undergraduate course that focused on the creation of holograms with Autodesk Maya

Research Assistant | DXARTS, 2008-2009

Center for Digital Arts and Experimental Media (DXARTS) University of Washington | dxarts.washington.edu Role: Research assistant to Shawn Brixey, director of DXARTS

- Translated historical experimental artworks to 3d animations for archival purposes
- · Modeling, lighting, animation in Autodesk Maya
- Technical photography

IT/Technology Studies Instructor, 2007-2008

Seattle Public Schools | seattleschools.org

Role: IT and instructor for Seattle Public Schools

- Provided IT support to staff, students and instructors
- Designed and taught a technology studies course, with an emphasis on creative digital output
- System administrator of network and storage servers

EXHIBITIONS, PUBLICATIONS, PRESENTATIONS, PRESS AND WORKSHOPS

2012 Mobile Processing Conference | | Workshop Instructor: Beginning Processing | Chicago, Illinois

Processing Chicago | Workshop Instructor: Beginning Processing+Kinect | Chicago, Illinois

Processing Chicago | Workshop Instructor: Beginning Processing | Chicago, Illinois

Spark Program Mentor | Instructor | Chicago, Illinois

Data Screens and Machines | Park Forest, Illinois

Processing Chicago | Presenter: Supercollider+Processing | Chicago, Illinois

Co-Founder of Processing Chicago, local node of Processing Cities

2011 Mobile Processing | Presenter | Chicago, Illinois

OxFF, UIC Department of Computer Science | Presenter | Chicago

Chicago Code Workshop | Presenter | Chicago, Illinois

SIGGRAPH 2011 | Vancouver, BC Canada

Incomplete Sense | Milwaukee Avenue Arts Festival | Chicago, Illinois

MFA Thesis Exhibition | Gallery 400 | Chicago, Illinois Super-signs | Hyde Park Art Center | Chicago, Illinois Somewhere in Time | Edinburgh, Scotland & Chicago

James Turrell's Mendota Stoppages and Roden Crater: When the Studio

and the Art Become One | HZ Journal, Issue #15

18-screen digital paint wall supports touch, iPad doodling | Engadget.com (November) **Researchers Paint on 20-foot Electronic Canvas** | Medill Reports Washington (November)

2009 Semi-Colon | Chicago, Illinois

2008 National Stereoscopic Assoc. Annual Convention | Grand Rapids, Michigan

DXARTS BFA Exhibition | Lawrimore Project | Seattle

AWARDS, FELLOWSHIPS AND ACADEMIC APPOINTMENTS

2011 Finalist, Image of Research Competition

University of Illinois at Chicago

2010 School of Art and Design Award

University of Illinois at Chicago

Graduate Research Assistantship Electronic Visualization Laboratory

2009 Board of Trustees Fellowship

School of Art and Design, University of Illinois at Chicago

2008 National Stereoscopic Association Special Award for Innovation